In the last video, along with the ideas of vector addition and scalar multiplication,
上个视频中 除了介绍向量加法和标量乘法外
I described vector coordinates,
我还讲了向量坐标
where there's this back and forth between,
讲解的时候
for example, pairs of numbers and two-dimensional vectors.
我们还提到数字对可以和二维向量互相转换
Now, I imagined the vector coordinates were already familiar to a lot of you,
现在我就默认你们都很熟悉向量坐标了
but there's another kind of interesting way to think about these coordinates,
我们可以用另一个有趣的视角来看待这些坐标
which is pretty central to linear algebra.
这个视角对线性代数相当重要
When you have a pair of numbers that's meant to describe a vector,
如果你有一对数字可以表示一个向量
like three negative two,
比如 3 和 -2
I want you to think about each coordinate as a scalar.
我希望你能将各坐标分别想成一个标量
Meaning, think about how each one stretches or squishes vectors.
也就是说 想象各坐标值对向量进行了拉伸或压缩
In the x, y coordinate system,
在 xy 坐标系中
there are two very special vectors,
有两个十分特殊的向量
the one pointing to the right with length one,
一个方向朝右 长度为 1
commonly called i hat or the unit vector in the x-direction,
通常称为 î 或 x 轴的单位向量
and the one pointing straight up with length one,
一个方向朝上 长度为 1
commonly called j hat or the univector in the y-direction.
通常称为 ĵ 或 y 轴的单位向量
Now, think of the x-coordinate of our vector as a scalar that scales i hat,
现在 将向量的 x 轴坐标看作一个缩放了 î 的标量
stretching it by a factor of three and the y-coordinate as a scalar that scales j hat,
该坐标将 î 拉长了三倍 将 y 轴坐标看作一个缩放了 ĵ 的标量
flipping it and stretching it by a factor of two.
该坐标翻转了 ĵ 并将其拉长了两倍
In this sense, the vector that these coordinates
而这两个坐标表示的向量
describe is the sum of two scaled vectors.
就是这两个经过缩放处理的向量的和
That's a surprisingly important concept,
这是个极其重要的概念
this idea of adding together two scaled vectors.
这种将两个经过缩放处理的向量相加的思路十分重要
Those two vectors, i hat and j hat,
顺便说一句 向量 î 和 ĵ
have a special name by the way.
有个特殊的名字
Together, they're called the basis of a coordinate system.
我们将这两者并称为坐标系的基
What this means basically is that when you think about coordinates as scalars,
换句话说 当你把坐标看作标量时
the basis vectors are what those scalars actually scale.
基向量就是标量缩放的对象
There's also a more technical definition,
我们还有更专业的定义
but I'll get to that later.
稍后再介绍
By framing our coordinate system in terms of these two special basis vectors,
从这两个特殊基向量的角度来研究坐标系
it raises a pretty interesting and subtle point.
就会引发一个有趣而微妙的问题
We could have chosen different basis vectors and gotten
其实我们可以取其它基向量
a completely reasonable new coordinate system.
建立另一个坐标系 这是完全合理的
For example, take some vector pointing up and to
举个例子 取某个方向指向右上方的向量
the right along with some other vector pointing down and to the right in some way.
和某个方向指向右下方的向量
Take a moment to think about all the different vectors that
思考一下
you can get by choosing two scalars,
这个时候如果你选择两个标量
using each one to scale one of the vectors,
对向量进行缩放
then adding together what you get.
再把缩放后的向量相加 你可以得到哪些向量
Which two-dimensional vectors can you reach by altering the choices of scalars?
改变标量 你又可以获得哪些二维向量呢？
The answer is that you can reach every possible two-dimensional vector.
答案是 你可以获得任意二维向量
And I think it's a good puzzle to contemplate why.
我觉得这是个值得思考的问题
A new pair of bases vectors like this still gives us a valid way to
虽然像这样换一对基向量 我们还是可以合法地
go back and forth between pairs of numbers and two-dimensional vectors,
在数字对和二维向量之间来回切换
but the association is definitely different from the one that you
但是数字与二维向量之间的关系
get using the more standard basis of i hat and j hat.
肯定与你用标准基 î 和 ĵ 时不同
That anytime we described vectors numerically,
只要我们用数字来描述向量
it depends on an implicit choice of what basis vectors we're using.
就会不可避免地受到基向量的影响
So, anytime that you're scaling two vectors and adding them like this,
所以像这样缩放两个向量并使两者相加的操作
it's called a linear combination of those two vectors.
称为这两个向量的线性组合
Where does this word linear come from?
为什么要用 “线性” 这个词呢？
Why does this have anything to do with lines?
与 “线” 有何关系呢？
Well, this isn't the etymology,
我比较喜欢这么想
but one way I like to think about it is that if you fix one
虽然未必是真正的词源 如果保持其中一个标量不变
of those scalars and let the other one change its value freely,
任意改变另一个标量的值
the tip of the resulting vector draws a straight line.
所得向量的头部会画出一条直线
Now, if you let both scalars range
如果同时改变两个标量
freely and consider every possible vector that you can get,
考虑一下你可能得到的所有向量吧
there are two things that can happen.
会有两种可能情况
For most pairs of vectors,
大多数向量对
you'll be able to reach every possible point in the plane.
能抵达平面上的所有可能点
Every two-dimensional vector is within your grasp.
因此你可以获得任意二维向量
However, in the unlucky case where your two original vectors happen to line up,
但如果不走运的话 两个原始向量共线了
the tip of the resulting vector is limited
那所得向量的头部
to just the single line passing through the origin.
就只能在一条穿过原点的直线上移动了
Actually, technically, there's a third possibility too,
从理论上讲 实际上还有第三种可能
both your vectors could be zero in which case you'd just be stuck at the origin.
两个向量都为 0 此时我们会陷在原点上
Here's some more terminology.
我们来讲些术语
The set of all possible vectors that you can reach with a linear combination of
已知一对向量 用其线性组合所获取的所有可能向量的集合
a given pair of vectors is called the span of those two vectors.
称为这两个向量的张成空间
So, restating what we just saw in this lingo,
因此 刚才的情况可以这么描述
the span of most pairs of 2D vectors is all vectors of 2D space.
大多数二维向量对的张成空间包含二维空间的所有向量
But when they line up, their span is all vectors whose tip sits on a certain line.
如果两个向量共线 则其张成空间包含所有头部落在某一直线上的向量
Remember how I said that linear algebra
还记得我之前说过
revolves around vector addition and scalar multiplication?
线性代数的核心就是向量加法和标量乘法吗？
Well, the span of two vectors is basically a way of asking what are
其实 两个向量的张成空间暗示了一个问题
all the possible vectors you can reach using only these two fundamental operations,
若只用向量加法和标量乘法这两个基本运算
vector addition and scalar multiplication?
你可以获得哪些可能向量？